University of Connecticut, Health Center Records 1997.0129
Archives & Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center, University of Connecticut Libraries
University of Connecticut, Health Center Records
undated, 1921-2012
1997.0129
Archives & Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center, University of Connecticut Libraries
117.15 Linear feet
The University of Connecticut Health Center is a vibrant organization composed of the School of Medicine, School of Dental Medicine, John Dempsey Hospital, the UConn Medical Group and University Dentists. The Health Center Records consist of correspondence, reports, minutes, administrative records, and personal papers pertaining to the creation and ongoing development of the medical and dental programs associated with the University of Connecticut.
University of Connecticut Health Center.
University of Connecticut.
History
The University of Connecticut Health Center is a vibrant organization composed of the School of Medicine, School of Dental Medicine, John Dempsey Hospital, the UConn Medical Group and University Dentists. Founded in 1961, the Health Center pursues a mission of providing outstanding health care education in an environment of exemplary patient care, research and public service. The Health Center's main campus is situated on 162 acres of wooded hilltop in the beautiful, historic community of Farmington. From this vantage point, the skyline of Hartford, the capital of Connecticut, can be seen about eight miles to the east. The University's main campus is in Storrs, about 30 miles east of Hartford. With approximately 3,900 employees, the Health Center is Farmington's largest employer and an important contributor to the local and regional economy.
Health Care Services
Through John Dempsey Hospital (204 general acute care beds and 20 nursery beds), the Health Center provides specialized and routine inpatient and outpatient services. John Dempsey Hospital has long been regarded as the premier facility in the region for neonatal intensive care and high-risk maternity. It is also widely recognized for its comprehensive cardiovascular, cancer and musculoskeletal services. Additionally, John Dempsey Hospital is home to the only Emergency Department in Connecticut's fast-growing Farmington Valley.
In June 2004, John Dempsey Hospital was awarded a prestigious silver Connecticut Quality Improvement Award Innovation Prize for its volunteer staff support of American Red Cross blood drives. Since 1987, the Connecticut Quality Improvement Awards have recognized Connecticut organizations that excel in managing quality improvement for success and growth.
Also offered are a wide range of ambulatory and primary care services on the Health Center campus in Farmington and in physician offices conveniently located in West Hartford, Simsbury and East Hartford. The UConn Medical Group is the largest medical practice in Greater Hartford, offering patients access to health care services from more than 350 Health Center physicians in more than 50 specialties.
Educational Programs
Dedicated to providing broad educational opportunities in the biomedical sciences, the Health Center offers degree programs in medicine (M.D.), dental medicine (D.M.D.), and biomedical science (Ph.D.); master's degree programs in public health and dental science; postdoctoral fellowships; residency programs providing specialty training for newly graduated physicians and dentists; and continuing education programs for practicing health care professionals. Combined degree programs, such as the M.D./Ph.D., D.M.D./Ph.D., Dental Clinical Specialty/Ph.D. and M.D./M.P.H. are also offered.
The UConn Health Center is the only academic health center in the nation where a medical school was founded concurrently with a dental school. As the schools took shape during the 1960s, their planners took advantage of their simultaneous evolution to forge strong links between them. Most notably, medical and dental students share an essentially common curriculum during the first two years of their four-year degree programs. During this period they study the basic medical sciences together. This experience provides UConn's dental students with an especially strong foundation in the biomedical sciences that undergird the dental profession. Reflecting its close ties to medicine, the dental school awards its graduates the D.M.D. - doctor of dental medicine.
Each year in Farmington, about 320 students work toward their medical doctor's degree and 160 toward their doctor of medical dentistry degree. Admission to each school is highly competitive, but both schools offer preferential consideration to qualified Connecticut residents in their admissions policies. School of Dental Medicine students have a long history of outstanding performance on the National Boards, ranking first among the country's 55 dental schools on these examinations in 2001 and again in 2003. In the years since the Health Center graduated its first students in 1972, 1,459 men and women have received their D.M.D. degree; 3,061 their M.D. degree.
Through a variety of residency programs, the School of Medicine provides postgraduate training for more than 550 newly graduated M.D.s each year. These physicians come from all over the country to acquire advanced skills in fields such as the surgical specialties, internal medicine, and primary care. Some of the residency training occurs on the Health Center's main campus, but much of it takes place in community hospitals in Greater Hartford - thus extending the Health Center's influence far beyond Farmington.
Research Programs
Since the Health Center's inception, its administration and faculty have been committed to maintaining high-quality research programs as part of the institution's fabric. This commitment has enabled the Health Center to recruit distinguished researchers with expertise in neuroscience, molecular biology, molecular pharmacology, biochemistry, cell physiology, toxicology, and endocrinology, among other fields. The Alcohol Research Center, is one of only 14 such federally supported centers in the nation; the Connecticut Clinical Chemosensory Research Center, one of five.
Clinical research is facilitated by the Lowell Weicker General Clinical Research Center and the Clinical Trials Unit. Intellectual endeavors of all kinds are supported by the Lyman Maynard Stowe Library.
Connecticut Health
UConn Health Center faculty, staff, residents, and students, participate in a variety of joint efforts to address public health and community health needs of citizens throughout our state. Under the umbrella of Connecticut Health, hundreds of projects have been developed in collaboration with other state agencies, city and town governments, community based organizations and the public to serve the poor and uninsured by providing better medical care, health education, and research.
Connecticut Health also strives to build and enhance relationships with the state legislature to bring health-conscious legislation, improved health care and a better quality of life to all our citizens. The development of new initiatives, projects and proposals are supported by Connecticut Health staff through brainstorming, data gathering, grant writing, and relationship building.
Our Campus
Construction of the Health Center's main campus began in 1966. The main complex occupies a prominent hilltop overlooking an interstate highway (I-84). This massive, circular building originally contained about 1.2 million square feet, seven miles of corridors, and 2,000 rooms. Its first major addition, the Andrew J. Canzonetti, MD Building, was dedicated in 1994. It added 94,000 square feet next to John Dempsey Hospital. The Health Center's Academic Research Building was opened in 1999. The impressive 11-story structure provides 170,000 square feet of state-of-the-art laboratory space.
Construction of a new 4-story, 99,000 square-foot musculoskeletal research and outpatient surgery facility began in late 2003, with completion and occupancy expected in early 2005. All told, the Health Center campus consists of 35 buildings totaling over 2 million square feet.
Additional information about the Health Center Campus is available on its website.
Scope and Content
The collection consists of correspondence, reports, minutes, administrative files, and personal papers pertaining to the creation and ongoing development of the medical and dental programs associated with the University of Connecticut. Materials in the collection encompases the period of 1921 to 2012, and include affirmative action plans, biennial budgets, faculty directories, department annual reports, advisory committee reports, and oral history tapes and transcripts.
Arrangement
Series I: State of Connecticut ( undated 1963-1986 ) includes materials published by the state that pertain directly to the University of Connecticut Health Center.
Series II: University of Connecticut ( undated, 1966-2005 ) consists of documents directly related to the Health Center.
Series III: Administration ( undated, 1968-1996 ) includes materials created by the administrative offices of the Health Center including directories, reports, correspondence, studies, and newspaper clippings.
Series IV: School of Medicine ( undated 1963-1996 ) consists of similar materials as listed above as they pertain to the School of Medicine and its departments and programs.
Series V: School of Dental Medicine ( undated, 1969-1995 ) consists of similar materials as listed above as they pertain to the School of Dental Medicine and its departments and programs.
Series VI: Dempsey Hospital ( undated, 1921, 1955-1992 ) includes reports, studies, correspondence, publications and manuals regarding University affiliated hospitals.
Series VII: Library ( undated, 1960-1997 ) includes reports, publications, correspondence and other materials relating to Stowe Library.
Series VIII: Biomedical Communications Department ( undated ) consists of publications. An unprocessed collection of photographs, transparencies and slides produced by the department has been transferred to the University Photograph Collection.
Series IX: Students ( undated, 1968-1996 ) is comprised primarily of publications.
Series X: Pharmacy ( undated, 1972-1991 ) contains published materials.
Series XI: Faculty Collections ( undated, 1968- ) includes minutes, personal papers and oral history recordings.
Series XII: 2012 Addition includes administrative records, ephemera, and optical disks. Materials in the series include topics such as: Liaison Committee on Medical Education (LCME) records and School of Medicine records.
Separated Material
The following materials have been separated from the collection and cataloged:
UConn House Call Dodd Peridocials
Public Health Happenings Dodd Peridocials
Graduate Student Handbook Dodd Peridocials
Beacon Dodd Peridocials
Caduceus Dodd Peridocials
HR Connections Dodd Peridocials
Telephone Directory Dodd Peridocials
Newsline Dodd Peridocials
Related Material
Archives & Special Collections has a substantial collection of materials pertaining to the University, its history, administration, faculty, staff and students. For detailed information on these collections please contact the curator or ask at the Reading Room desk.
Access
The collection is open and available for research.
Academic health centers-- Connecticut.; Administrative Records.; Audio cassettes.; Audio visual materials.; Blueprints.; Books.; Bylaws.; Correspondence.; Dental health education--Connecticut.; Farmington, Conn.; Financial Records.; Fliers. [printed matter]; Interviews.; John Dempsey Hospital.; Medical education-- Connecticut.; Minutes.; Newsletters.; Notebooks.; Notes.; Oral Histories.; Photocopies.; Photographs.; Press releases.; Publications.; Universities and colleges--Administration.; University of Connecticut. Health Center.; University of Connecticut. School of Dental Medicine.; University of Connecticut. School of Medicine.; Videocassettes.
- Series I: State of Connecticut, undated 1963-1986
  - Reports of the Commission for Higher Education, Department of Higher Education (Box 1)
  - Papers of the Connecticut Association of Directors of Health, 1963-1986 (Box 2-4)
  - Report of Joint Legislative Committee 1975, reports from the Department of Higher Education (Box 5)
- Series II: University of Connecticut, undated, 1966-2005
  - Publications of the University containing references to the Health Center and letters from the Board of Trustees to the Governor, Minutes of the University of Connecticut Hospital Board of Trustees, Economic Impact of the Health Center, 1966,1971, 1974, 1977-1978, 1988, 1992 (Box 6)
  - Health Affairs Committee, Board of Trustees, 2000 January - 2005 March (Box 133-136)
    General note
    The Minutes for the Health Affairs Committee, also known as "HAC", cover the period: Jan. 26, 2000 to June 18, 2002. At the next meeting after that date, the "Health Affairs Committee" became the "Board of Directors", and these minutes cover the period: September 9, 2002 - March 1, 2005.
- Series III: Administration, undated, 1968-1996
  - Organization charts, Equal Employment, Responses to Questions of Dr. Cohen, Photographs of administration retreat, report of Attorney General Lieberman, 1968, 1975-1977, 1988, 1992-1994, 1997 (Box 7)
  - Biennial budgets, approval of CT Scanner, Master Plan, Fiscal and Budget reports, Policy on Safety Training, 1981, 1984-1990, 1993-94,1994-95 (Box 8)
  - Salary Study, Operational Guidelines, Equipment grants, Biomolecular Structure Analysis Center, Research Report on Med/Dent schools, Research Administration Manual, Research Notes, 1960s, 1972, 1984, 1986-1987, 1991-1994 (Box 9)
  - Miscellaneous papers from VP office and administration, 1968-1972 (Box 10)
  - Miscellaneous papers from VP office and administration Testimony: Unallocated Balances, 1972-1991, 1/16/97 (Box 11)
  - Research activities and notes; Research and Scholarly Activities. Research Opportunities Booklet, 1969-1994, 1996-1998 (Box 12)
  - Affirmative Action Plans, 1977-1990 (Box 13-17)
  - Health Center Report, 1965-1969, 1976-1981 (Box 17)
  - Newspaper Clippings regarding Health Center, News Release Dean of Dental School named, 1997 (Box 18-19)
  - Radiation Safety Annual Reports; CLAC Center for Laboratory Animal Care annual report, 1975-1977-1983/84,1985/86 (Box 19)
  - Health Center Quarterly; UConn Health & Science, 1984-1997 (Box 20)
  - UConn Health & Science"; Vista, 1997-1998 (Box 20a)
  - Faculty/Staff Directories, Alumni directories, 1972-1975 (Box 21)
  - Newsline, 1989-1996 (Box 22)
  - Newsline, 1997 (Box 22a)
  - General Clinical Research Center GCRC newsletter, Preliminary Group Practice Report, Slides of scenes of Health Center construction, Job Health and Safety Committee, ca. 1972, 1987-1988, 1995, 1997 (Box 23)
  - Long Range Information Systems Plans; Information Technology News, 1982-1986, 1992, 1995 (Box 24)
  - Telephone directories, 1980-1988 (Box 25)
  - Telephone directories, 1989-1998 (Box 26)
  - Minority Student Affairs report, Health Center Annual Reports, Bits & Bytes, Human Resources Reorganization Services, 1982-1990, 1955-1997 (Box 27)
  - Planning Documents, CyberRail, 1967 (Box 28)
  - Planning Documents, Architectural Albums, Health Center Committee, Work Program for Health Center, Lester Gorsline Associates, 1964-1968 (Box 29)
  - Planning Documents: Farmington Group, Master Site Study, 1973 (Box 30)
  - Planning Documents, Bibliography, UCHC First Two Decades, Dental and Medical School Physical Plan, Groundbreaking, Letters of Acceptance, Development of School of Medicine, Women's Caucus, H. Shuchman, "Political History of the Health Center," Exhibits from litigation Lasher Goldman vs. State, 1968, 1971, 1974, 1977-1978, 1981 (Box 31)
  - Special Events,Union, Data Services Annual Reports, Health Center Association, Office of Public Information publications, UCHC Salutes You, Directline, 1996-1997 (Box 32)
  - Dedication of Health Center, 25th anniversary celebration, 30th anniversary celebration, Alumni Reunion, 1972, 1977, 1986, 1991, 1997 (Box 33)
  - Broadcast messages, 2002-2005 (Box 128)
    - UCHC Policy statements, 2003 (Box 128)
      - Research Misconduct, Whistleblower Protection, Data Ownership, HIPPA Fundraising
    - UCHC Administration, Office of VP
      - Miscellaneous, 2005 (Box 128)
      - Budget, FY 2001/2, FY 2002/3, 2001-2003 (Box 128)
      - Affirmative Action, 2003-2004 (Box 128)
      - Minority Student Affairs, 2005? (Box 129)
    - UCHC Administration, Publications (Box 129)
      - Miscellaneous, 2002-2005
    - UCHC Administration, Human Resources, 1988-2005 (Box 129)
- Series IV: School of Medicine, undated 1963-1996
  - [Note: Often includes School of Dental Medicine papers when both schools were included.]
  - School of Medicine Annual Reports, 1963-1981 (Box 34)
  - School of Medicine Annual Reports, 1981-1996 (Box 35)
  - School of Medicine Faculty Biographies and Papers, 1975-1976 (Box 36)
  - School of Medicine Faculty Biographies and Papers, 1976-1977 (Box 37)
  - School of Medicine Faculty Biographies and Papers, 1977-1978 (Box 38)
  - Goals/Objectives 1975, Biography Ward Bullock, AAMC Accreditation, Faculty list, Faculty outreach, SOM organization, Dr. Patterson papers, Faculty meetings, Medical Science Retreat, 1967-1971, 1975, 1977-1980, 1989, 1994 (Box 39)
  - Medical Student Affairs papers, Travelers Center on Aging, "Successful Aging," Geriatric Education Center papers, Commencement, Uniform Crime Report, Connecticut Cancer Institute, 1969-1996 (Box 40)
  - Dean Patterson misc. papers, Dean of Academic Affairs annual reports, Blue Ribbon Commission report, Basic Medical Sciences Policy and Procedures, 1969-1984, 1990 (Box 41)
  - Continuing Medical Education papers, 1976-1980 (Box 42)
  - Continuing Medical Education papers, Preclinical and Graduate Education, Affiliates, miscellaneous papers, Continuing Education Programs, 1969-1997 (Box 43)
  - Dean of School of Medicine papers, Memorandum, 1968-1974, 1997 (Box 44)
  - Second Year Committee papers, Medical Sciences papers, 1967-1976 (Box 45)
  - Dean of School of Medicine papers, Dean's Advisory Committee papers, 1969, 1973-1976 (Box 46)
  - Dean's Advisory Committee papers, School of Medicine papers, 1971-1974 (Box 47)
  - Dean's Advisory Committee papers, 1970-1971 (Box 48)
  - Dean's Advisory Committee papers, School of Medicine papers, 1972-1975 (Box 49)
  - School of Medicine Collective Reports, Dean's Advisory Committee papers, 1970-1974 (Box 50)
  - School of Medicine Council Minutes, 1971-1975 (Box 51)
  - Committee on Undergraduate Medical Education: papers, Questionnaire and Summary, School of Medicine Council Minutes, School of Medicine Steering Committee, 1968-1979 (Box 52)
  - Clinical Medicine and Health Care (department) papers, "Expenditures for Health Care Services," Curriculum Committee papers, Financial Aid (department), University Physicians: Referral Guide, Newsletter UConn Physicians, Five Year Plan (various departments), 1970-1971, 1973, 1980, 1983-1984, 1992-1995 (Box 53)
  - Department of Anesthesiology annual reports, Community Medicine annual reports, Dept of Community Medicine misc. papers, newsletter CICHS (Center for International community Health Studies, 1970-1997 (Box 54)
  - "Evaluation Preceptorship Training," Department of Family Medicine annual reports, Recommendations for the development of Family Medicine, 1971-1988 (Box 55)
  - Community Medicine and Health Care annual reports, 1981-1997 (Box 56)
  - Relationship between Clinical Medicine and Medical Specialties, Organization of Medicine and Pediatrics, Clinical Medicine annual report, Department of Medicine annual reports, 1967-1968, 1975-1988 (Box 57)
  - Department of Medicine annual reports, 1983-1996 (Box 58)
  - Department of Medicine annual reports, 1996-1997 (Box 58a)
  - Laboratory Medicine annual reports, 1969-1996 (Box 59)
  - Laboratory Medicine annual reports, 1996-1997 (Box 59a)
  - Neurology annual reports, Department standards in Neurosurgery, Nuclear Medicine annual reports, Internal Medicine Residency, 1974-1997 (Box 60)
  - Neurology annual reports, Obstetrics/Gynecology annual reports, Orthopedic Surgery annual reports, 1967, 1974-1998 (Box 61)
  - Orthopedic Surgery annual reports, 1988-1997 (Box 61a)
  - Pediatrics annual reports, Pediatric Residency and Training Center, PRTC, Organization of Medicine and Pediatrics revised, 1968-1997 (Box 62)
  - Psychiatry papers and annual reports, 1969-1997 (Box 63)
  - Radiology annual reports, Department of Diagnostic Imaging and Therapeutics annual report, 1971-1997 (Box 64)
  - Surgery annual reports, Surgical Dialogue newsletter 1988-1996, Annual Advances in Toxicology, 1971-1996 (Box 65)
  - Surgery annual reports, 1987-1992 (Box 66)
  - Surgery annual reports, Anatomy annual reports, 1969-1997 (Box 67)
  - Surgery annual reports, 1996-1997 (Box 67a)
  - Biochemistry annual reports, 1968-1997 (Box 68)
  - Anatomic Pathology annual reports, Pathology annual reports, 1969-1987 (Box 69)
  - Pathology annual reports, Immunology booklet, 1983, 1988-1997 (Box 70)
  - Physiology annual reports, Research in Health Education annual reports, 1970-1997 (Box 71)
  - Microbiology annual reports, Pharmacology annual reports, 1969-1997 (Box 72)
  - Pharmacology annual reports, 1996-1997 (Box 72a)
  - Clerkship in Medicine, Syllabus Office, Subject Committees, Selective and Elective Clerkship, 1968, 1970-1976 (Box 73)
  - Selective and Elective Clerkship, 1974-1980 (Box 74)
  - School of Medicine, 1968-1991 (Box 75)
  - Undergraduate Medical Education (ICM) annual reports and papers, Departmental and selective Clerkships, 1969-1986 (Box 76)
  - "Public Health Happenings," Medical Education Database / Liaison Committee on Medical Education, 1980, 1986-1997 (Box 77)
  - Graduate Student Research Day, Student Research Opportunities "Blue Book", Proposed master's Program in Pathology, Internship and Residency papers and catalogs, 1971-1992 (Box 78)
  - Pappanikou Center, 2002-2003 (Box 129)
  - Miscellaneous, 2002-2004 (Box 129)
  - Clinical Departments
    - Surgery, 2003 (Box 129)
  - Publications-- James Walker tribute, 2004 (Box 129)
- Series V: School of Dental Medicine, undated, 1969-1995
  - School of Dental Medicine annual reports, School of Dental Medicine papers, 1975-1984, 1988 (Box 79)
  - School of Dental Medicine annual reports, 1985-1989 (Box 80)
  - School of Dental Medicine annual reports, 1990-1993 (Box 81)
  - School of Dental Medicine annual reports, 1996-1997 (Box 81a)
  - ADA Accreditation, 1976 (Box 82)
  - ADA Accreditation: Survey Manuals, 1978 (Box 83)
  - ADA Accreditation: Advanced Specialty Programs, 1978 (Box 84)
  - ADA Accreditation: Related Materials & Predoctoral Dental Programs, 1978 (Box 85)
  - ADA Accreditation: Advanced Specialty Programs, 1986 (Box 86)
  - ADA Accreditation: Course Outlines & Basic Sciences Subject Committees. Self-study Manual 1, 1986 (Box 87)
  - ADA Accreditation: Self-study Manuals 2-3, 1986 (Box 88)
  - ADA Accreditation: Self-study Manual 4. Self-study Progress Reports. Biographies, Bibliographies & Professional Summaries 1976, 1976, 1986 (Box 89)
  - Biographies, Bibliographies & Professional Summaries, 1977-1978 (Box 90)
  - Dental Students: Handbook, Student Affairs Annual Report, Budget, Class Roster, Organization, Papers, Misc. resumes, Dean's Advisory Committee, Faculty Meetings, Connecticut Dental Student Journal, Student Scientific Days, Newsletter (School of Dental Medicine), 5th Annual Medical/Dental Student Scientific Research Day, 1968-1995 (Box 91)
  - Dental Medicine Council Minutes, 1972-1978 (Box 92)
  - Notes of Interest to Dental Students, Endodontics Dept.-History and Misc. Papers, Student Newsletter, Curriculum Objectives, 1975-1993 (Box 93)